Ewa Slusarek papers 1982-1990 CPAA 93-04
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University, New Britain
Ewa Slusarek Papers
1982-1990
Ewa Slusarek
CPAA 93-04
2 boxes (2 linear ft.)
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University
Ewa Slusarek and her husband Jacek were involved in the Solidarity support movement in the United States after introduction of Martial Law in Poland on December 13, 1981. The Slusarek's established the Solidarity Support Committee of Rhode Island to aid the Solidarity Labor Union organization in Poland. Such support committees were established in several states and also worldwide. There was a call for the establishment of an umbrella organization that would coordinate activities of these support organizations. In 1983 a group of representatives from these organizations met in Buffalo, NY and formed an organization called "Conference of Solidarity Support Committees" (CSSC). The collection includes documentation and activities related to the formation of these organizations, broad correspondence and related legal documents, press releases and clippings.
Biographical Note
Ewa Slusarek, b. Kiersznowski was born in Banghor, Scotland in 1948. She has lived in the U.S. since 1957. She received a B.A. in history and political science from the University of Delaware in 1973. Ms. Slusarek worked as a bank auditor and executive and also served as president of Women Center in Providence from 1981 to 1986. Ewa Slusarek founded the Solidarity Support Committee of Rhode Island in 1982 and served as the North American Coordinator for Conference of Solidarity Support Organizations (CSSO) between 1982 and 1989. She was also active in local Polish American organizations such as the Polish National Home in Providence and Polish Sub-Committee of Rhode Island Heritage Commission.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The collection includes records of several non-profit organizations that supported and lobbied for the Polish underground Solidarity movement in addition to personal papers of Ewa Slusarek. Solidarity support organizations operated in the US and Western Europe between 1982 and 1989. Material was donated by Ewa Slusarek who was active in Solidarity International, Solidarity Support Committee of Rhode Island, and worldwide Conference of Solidarity Support Organizations. Material includes: correspondence, press releases, statements, minutes, membership lists, financial records, legal documents, news clippings, and speeches. There are also some records pertaining to Rhode Island Polish American community.
Arrangement
Material in the collection is arranged by various Solidarity support organizations and is kept in chronological order.
The collection is open for research.
Collection was donated to the archives by Ewa Slusarek in 1993.
Related Material
For related material see the following collections: Andre B. Blaszczynski Papers (CPAA 87-105) Irene Dubicka Morawska Papers (CPAA 93-03) Ludmil A. Chotkowski Papers (CPAA 90-14) Elizabeth Wasiutynski Papers (CPAA 91-03)
Search Terms
Solidarity Support Committee of Rhode Island.; Solidarity International.; Conference of Solidarity Support Organizations.; Polish Americans -- Rhode Island -- Politics and government.; Polish Americans -- Connecticut -- Politics and government.; Poles -- Foreign countries.; Membership lists.; Minutes.; Correspondence.; Speeches.; Financial records.; Legal documents.; Press releases.; Programs.; Clippings.
Container List
[The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.]
- Solidarity support organizations
  - Ewa Slusarek - speeches and private papers, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Polish National Home, Providence, Rhode Island, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Polish Sub-Committee of Rhode Island Heritage Commission., 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Solidarity International - declaration, program of activity, appeals, press releases., 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Solidarity International - "The need" draft of objectives and goals., 1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Solidarity International - by-laws, drafts, manual for chapter., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Solidarity International - financial records., 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Solidarity International - minutes., 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Solidarity International - addresses of activists, 1980's (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Solidarity International - membership application A-M., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Solidarity International - membership application N-Z., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Solidarity International - mail log., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Solidarity International - mailing lists, telephones, contacts, 1980's (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Solidarity International - correspondence A-G., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Solidarity International - correspondence H-O, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Solidarity International - correspondence P-Z, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Solidarity International - lists of arrested and interned., 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Lists of arrested and interned compiled by Committee in Support of Solidarity, N.Y., 1980's (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lists of arrested and interned compiled by Comite de Coordination du Syndicat "Solidarnosc" en France., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Lists of arrested and interned compiled by Amnesty International, London, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Repressions in Poland., 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Solidarity International, Connecticut Chapter - speeches, letters, addresses, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Solidarity Support Committee of Rhode Island - documents, membership application, by-laws., 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Solidarity Support Committee of Rhode Island -activities, press releases., 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Solidarity Support Committee of Rhode Island - minutes., 1982-1986 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Publicity re: films, plays on Solidarity, 1980's (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Lectures, exhibits, conferences on Polish and Solidarity issue., 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Press clippings., 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Posters, fliers, broadsides, 1980's (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Conference of Solidarity Support Organizations - resolution, Letter of Agreement, membership., 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Conference of Solidarity Support Organizations meetings in Cleveland and in Providence, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Conference of Solidarity Support Organizations meetings - Norwalk; London; Jersey City, Providence and Lund., 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Conference of Solidarity Support Organizations in Canada., 1986 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Janek Wisniewski Fund, Chicago., 1982 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - International Fund for Polish Students., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - The Friends of Solidarity Families Project -statements, by-laws, correspondence., 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - NSZZ Solidarnosc Factory Commission Sponsorship Program - correspondence., 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, between 1981-1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing correspondence - Solidarity Support Committee of Rhode Island (SSCofRI), 1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Outgoing correspondence - SSCofRI., 1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Outgoing correspondence - SSCofRI., 1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Outgoing correspondence - SSCofRI., 1986 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Outgoing correspondence - SSCofRI., 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Outgoing correspondence - SSCofRI., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Outgoing correspondence - SSCofRI., 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Incoming correspondence - SSCofRI., 1981-1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Incoming correspondence - SSCofRI., 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - SSCofRI correspondence re: Ryszard Kolacz and Grazyna Zychowska., 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Coordinating Office Abroad NSZZ Solidarnosc, Brusseles, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - NSZZ Solidarity information office in Holland., 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Committee in Support of Solidarity N.Y., 1981-1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Support of Solidarity, Boston., 1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Philadelphia Committee in Support of Solidarity., 1982 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Committee in Support of Solidarity, Cleveland, Ohio., 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Friends of Solidarity, Washington., 1984 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Solidarity support group, Los Angeles., 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - PROTEST Solidarity support group, Washington, DC., 1982 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Confederacy of Independent Poland, New York., 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Friends of Solidarnosc Association, Vancouver, Canada - by-laws and constitution., 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Canadian Polish Congress, Inc. - "A chronicle of death in Poland"., 1985 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Solidarity with Solidarity, London., 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Support of Solidarnosc, Melbourne, Australia., 1981-1986 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Committee in Support of Solidarity, Southern Sweden., 1982 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Polish Democratic Party, Munich, Germany., 1988 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Kontakt, Paris, France., 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Pomost, Chicago., 1983-1989 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - The North American Study Center for Polish Affairs - STUDIUM, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - International Trade Union on Polish issues., 1982 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - US Congress on Polish issues., 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Dubicka-Morawska, Irene "American Polonia: Solidarity and Independence"., 1982 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Solidarity Information Office in Canada., 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Catalogs of Polish press and publication, 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Varia - publications, appeals, pamphlets,letters., 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Oversized folder Proclamation by The Mayor of Providence, R.I. of Lech Walesa Day, December 10, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 37)